I've been tossing and turning
我已经在帐篷里
in my tent for an hour or so.
辗转难眠一小时左右
Inuko's gone home.
犬子回家了
See you tomorrow.
明天见
Dinner was simple with cup rice.
晚餐用杯饭简单解决了
The Hayashi rice was delicious!
香雅饭好好吃
Then…
然后
Drinking cocoa and watching the sunrise while solo-camping is the best thing ever!
独自露营时一边喝可可 一边看日出可是最棒的享受哦
So, I decided to follow Nadeshiko's advice
于是我决定听从抚子的建议
and went to bed early in my sleeping bag.
早早就钻进睡袋准备就寝
But after those day campers left,
但那些日间露营的人回去后
I was the only one left in this campsite.
这座露营场就只剩我一个
There wasn't a single streetlight around,
而且周遭一盏路灯都没有
and the sky was covered by thick clouds,
天空还被厚厚着云层遮住
making the campsite completely dark.
让露营场彻底变得一片漆黑
And that's when
就在这时候
I had the urge to use the loo.
我突然有了一点尿意
But since I didn't want to fumble around in the dark to get to the toilet,
但因为我不想摸黑去上厕所
I kept squirming in my sleeping bag.
就在睡袋里翻来覆去
Then, a strange noise
结果不知从哪里
started coming from somewhere.
开始传来了奇怪的声响
I thought I'd wait until the noise stopped so I could go,
本来想说等声响停止后 再去上厕所
but I ended up waiting for over 30 minutes!
所以我竖耳倾听了半小时左右
Now, I'm on the verge of breaking through my limits!
如今我的尿意已经到达爆发边缘了
LAID-BACK CAMP SEASON 3
《摇曳露营△ (第三季)》
EPISODE 12 2ND APRIL CHERRY BLOSSOM VIEWING CAMP
(第12话 4月2号 赏樱露营)
This rustling sound…
这个沙沙声
Based on my camping experience,
透过之前在露营中学到的经验 我知道
I knew it was definitely not the sound of the tent swaying in the wind.
这绝对不是帐篷随风摇晃 而发出的声音
It was clearly an animal.
明显是动物发出来的声音
The animals that could be around here
说到这附近会有的动物
include raccoons, civets, deer, monkeys, boars,
那就是狸猫 白鼻心 羚羊 猴子 山猪
and bears!
以及熊
It's fine if it's just a raccoon,
如果只是狸猫倒还好
but what if it's a boar or a bear? What will I do then?
但万一遇到山猪或熊的话 该怎么办才好?
"BEWARE OF BEARS IN NAMBU" Was there a bear sign
(小心熊出没 南部町) 这个露营场
in this town?
有小心熊出没的惯用告示牌吗
I remember the toilet is about 20 metres from here.
我记得从这里到厕所大约20米
I could slowly make my way there.
万一慢慢走过去
If I run into a bear,
结果遇到熊的话
I must never make eye contact.
绝对不能跟它对到眼
I should avoid looking it in the eyes and slowly back away
尽量面对它
and create distance between us…
慢慢往后退 和它拉开距离…
And I'd surely wet myself.
这样的话 绝对会漏尿的
I should just make a run for it
干脆用冲的跑进厕所
and lock myself in the toilet!
把自己关在里面吧
No.
不行…
If I do that, I'll be stuck in there until dawn.
这样就只能一直在里面待到早上了
Plus, the toilet didn't look that sturdy.
而且那间厕所看起来也不是很坚固
If a bear attacks,
要是被熊攻击
-I'd have no way to defend myself. -Roar!
-根本毫无招架之力 -熊
Oh… It was just these cats…
原…原来是猫啊
I feel sleepy after being liberated both physically and mentally.
在身心都得到解放后 突然有点想睡了
So cold…
好冷…
There's nothing else to do anyway. I should go to sleep.
反正也无事可做 还是赶紧睡觉吧
It's from Rin.
是凛传来的
What's this link?
这是什么连结啊?
"YOU CAN SEE THE MAGLEV TRAIN FROM THIS HILL" This looks like a live camera feed.
(可以看到磁浮列车的山丘) 这是即时影像吧?
Mt. Hanatori?
(花鸟山一本杉公园网络摄影机) 花鸟山?
Creepy!
好可怕
That scared the heck out of me!
很可怕耶
I figured you'd be bored at your camp.
我想说你一个人露营 现在应该正闲得发慌吧
It's a little early, but I'm getting ready for bed now.
虽然还有点早 但我准备要睡了
How are things on your side?
你那边怎么样?
I took it easy.
过得超惬意的
It's a nice place
虽然数量不多 但也有开一些樱花
with some cherry blossoms. Not a lot, but some.
是个不错的地方哦
In the mountains of Fujikawa, right?
是在富士川町的山区那一带吧?
Yeah.
没错
I even made tomato pasta with the Akeno tomatoes you all gave me.
我还用你们送的伴手礼 明野西红柿做了西红柿意大利面
It was really delicious.
真的超好吃
You used them for pasta?
凛拿来煮意大利面吗
Sounds divine.
听起来不错嘛
The tomatoes taste good raw,
虽然西红柿生吃也很好吃
but cooking them makes them even sweeter and flavourful!
但经过熬煮口感会变得更加鲜甜 让人忍不住一口接一口呢
I know what you mean.
我懂
How's your campsite?
你那边的露营场感觉怎么样?
Just like you said,
跟你说的一样
there are a lot of cherry blossoms,
这里开了许多樱花
and it's pretty empty.
而且还没什么人
Definitely a hidden gem.
确实是个私房景点呢
So hidden that I'm the only one here now.
不过也因为太隐密 现在这里只剩我一个
So today, I spent a leisurely day
所以我今天就一边赏樱
watching cherry blossoms and drinking Saratoga Coolers.
一边喝萨拉托加酷乐 度过了悠闲的一天
What's that?
那是什么?
A mocktail made by mixing lime juice and ginger ale.
就是一种把莱姆 加进姜汁汽水的饮料
I have some ingredients left, so I'll make it for you tomorrow.
材料还有剩 明天再做给你喝吧
Looking forward to it.
我会好好期待的
Oh, also,
对了
Inuko rode her road bike over to my place this evening.
傍晚犬子还突然骑着公路自行车 跑来我这边
By the way, what are you doing in such a dark place?
是说 你在那么暗的地方做什么呀?
Aren't you at a place called Mt. Hanatori right now?
你现在不是在一个 叫花鸟山的地方吗
I'm on my way home.
我在回家的路上
The cherry blossoms here are lit up at night,
因为这里的樱花晚上会点灯
so I took a brief detour.
我只是绕过来看看而已
They're stunning! I didn't know there was a spot like this.
好漂亮 原来还有这种景点啊
I'm glad you're enjoying your solo camp.
看你这么享受单人露营 我就放心了
I think I get why you like solo-camping so much now.
我好像能稍微理解你 为什么会热衷于单人露营了
Well, I should head home.
那么 我差不多该回家了
Be careful not to catch a cold.
你小心别感冒咯
You too. Take care on your way back.
你也是 路上小心哦
See you tomorrow.
明天见
What's this now?
这次又是什么呀?
Isn't this the thing
这是每年春天时
they light up every spring?
都会点亮的那个东西吧
So you can watch the live camera feed of it too.
原来还能用即时影像看到啊
It's beautiful.
挺漂亮的嘛
All right.
那么
I'd better head home before I catch a cold.
我也趁还没感冒前 赶紧回家吧
It's a sea of cherry blossoms!
这里开了好多樱花
It's the perfect spot for our cherry blossom viewing camp.
正适合当作赏樱露营的地点呢
Indeed.
就是说啊
Aki-chan!
小明
Oh, there they come.
来了…
Thanks for coming early to save us a spot, Aki-chan.
小明 辛苦你提前来占位了
There's plenty of space even if I didn't.
就算不提前来占位 这里的位置也能随便挑啦
Hey, Aki-chan!
哈啰 小明
Well, well, Chibi Inuko tagged along too.
什么啊 小犬子也跟来了吗
I heard you were having a barbecue.
因为我听说你们要烤肉
So you came for the meat, huh?
原来是为了肉而来的吗
This is the second time we've all come camping together
这是继伊豆露营后
since the Izu Camp.
再次以这样的组合一起来露营呢
You're right.
对呀
All right!
好
Now that everyone's here,
既然大家都到齐了
the cherry blossom viewing camp can begin!
那就开始来赏樱露营吧
Let's start!
开始吧
Ms. Toba,
老师
you said to leave the food for the camp to you.
你之前说赏樱料理就交给你负责
So, we're having a barbecue?
原来是要烤肉啊
That's right. But specifically,
没错 虽然说是烤肉
we're having Jingisukan (Genghis Khan).
但准确来说是成吉思汗烤肉
Yay! Jingisukan!
好耶 是成吉思汗烤肉
You like Jingisukan, Akari?
朱莉喜欢吃成吉思汗烤肉吗
At our house, we have Jingisukan for dinner about three times a month.
我们家每个月大约会有三天的 晚餐都吃成吉思汗烤肉
That's quite often.
一个月吃三次还满惊人的耶
So our family has high standards
所以我们家的人
for Jingisukan.
对成吉思汗烤肉的要求还挺高的哦
Right, Aoi?
对吧 小葵
Maybe.
或许吧
I saw it on TV.
之前我在电视上看到介绍
Apparently, those in Hokkaido enjoy Jingisukan
听说北海道人 都会边吃成吉思汗烤肉边赏樱
and I thought it sounded great.
就觉得满不错的
I've heard that too.
我也有听过这件事
"PORK, LAMB" And for Jingisukan,
(猪肉 羊肉) 而且吃成吉思汗烤肉的话
all you need to do is marinate the meat in the sauce.
只需要把肉放进酱汁里调味就好
Even if you're too tipsy to see straight, it's no problem.
就算醉到看不清楚也没有问题
Ms. Toba is as lively as ever today.
老师今天依然不改本色呢
Anyway, I've marinated both the lamb and pork in the sauce.
不过我姑且还是先把羊肉 和猪肉都用酱料腌制过了
For anyone who doesn't like lamb, there's pork.
如果有人不敢吃羊肉 可以吃猪肉
Additionally,
另外
besides Jingisukan, I bought an unusual type of meat today.
今天除了有成吉思汗烤肉 我还买了一种比较少见的肉哦
This may come as a surprise to you girls,
你们可能会有点惊讶
but ta-da!
就是这个
CROAK
(呱)
"SELF-CENSORED" Frog meat.
(自主规制) 青蛙肉
F… Frog?
青…青蛙?
Why… Why would you buy this?
为…为什么会买这个?
That's real frog meat.
完全是货真价实的青蛙嘛
Well…
这个嘛
I thought, since we have a chance to have Jingisukan,
我想说难得有机会烤成吉思汗烤肉
why not buy the meat from a speciality shop?
不如就去肉品专卖店买肉吧
"TAKABAYASHI MEATS" So I went
(肉之高林) 所以就跑去某间
to a meat speciality store in Fujikawa Town.
位于富士川町的肉品专卖店
OSTRICH, FROG
(鸵鸟肉 青蛙肉)
"RATTLESNAKE, CROCODILE" Turns out,
(蟒蛇肉 鳄鱼肉) 结果那边
they also sell exotic meats.
其实也是一间卖特殊肉品的店
Rattlesnake and crocodile…
响…响尾蛇肉和鳄鱼肉
I was recommended the frog meat. They said it tastes like chicken
后来店员推荐我买青蛙肉 说吃起来像鸡肉 接受度应该很高
so I bought it.
所以我就买来了
If it tastes like chicken, why not just eat chicken?
吃起来像鸡肉的话 直接吃鸡肉不就好了吗
As the visual was unpleasantly of a frog,
因为它的视觉上实在太青蛙
the meat was quickly battered and deep-fried.
于是赶紧油炸糊弄过去
Taste test.
试吃
Tastes like regular fried chicken.
吃起来很像普通的炸鸡
It's pretty good, actually.
确实满好吃的
But the fact
不过
my mind keeps reminding me that this is frog
"这是青蛙"的事实 一直浮现在我的脑海中
makes it hard for me to really enjoy it.
没办法好好地品尝
You took the words right out of my mouth.
没错
Actually, I'm not a big fan of lamb.
其实我有点不太敢吃羊肉
Why not, Ena?
惠那 你为什么不敢吃羊肉呀?
I don't really like that gameyness, I suppose.
应该是因为它有种独特的臭味吧
Aoi, is Jingisukan "gamey"?
小葵 成吉思汗烤肉有什么臭味吗
Beats me.
不知道耶
We've been eating it since we were little.
毕竟我们从小就很常吃
Maybe we're just used to it.
可能已经习惯了吧
Tuck in, everyone!
那么 各位开动吧
I'm digging in!
我要开动了
It looks so good!
看起来真好吃
Put the vegetables at the bottom
只要像这样把菜放在下面
and then grill the meat on top,
然后在上面烤肉
the meat juices will drip down
滴下来的肉汁就会渗进蔬菜里 真的很好吃呢
Akari, you sure know a lot.
朱莉果然懂很多呢
It's so delicious!
好好吃哦
Lamb is so tasty!
羊肉真好吃
The pork goes perfectly with the sauce! So good!
猪肉跟酱汁也超搭的 好好吃
Scrumptious!
真的很好吃呢
It's quite nice, enjoying Jingisukan
一边赏樱 一边吃成吉思汗烤肉
while flower viewing.
真是相当不错呢
Let's do this again next year!
明年再办一次吧
Huh?
咦
What's wrong, you two?
你们两个怎么了?
CALLING GRANDMA
(来电 葵)
Hello? Grandma?
喂 奶奶
We're camping right now,
我们现在在露营
and we're having Jingisukan.
然后大家一起吃了成吉思汗烤肉
But I thought it tasted completely different from what we normally have at home.
但总觉得吃起来的味道 跟我们家煮的完全不一样
Then,
然后
"PORK" Ms. Toba brought out another bag
(猪肉) 老师还带了一包
of pork marinated in the Jingisukan sauce.
用成吉思汗酱汁腌渍过的猪肉
When we had that,
结果我们烤来吃之后
we realised that was the taste we knew of Jingisukan…
发现这个才有我们家的 成吉思汗烤肉的味道
So,
葵
you have found out, Aoi.
你终于发现了吗
The truth is, for generations,
其实我们家的成吉思汗烤肉 从以前开始就一直是…
…pork.
用猪肉
Grand.. Grandma!
奶…奶奶
You lied to us all this time?
你骗了我们吗
Calm down, Aoi.
葵 你冷静一点
The world is full of lies.
这种谎言在世上很常见
Do you know?
你知道吗
The yakitori bentos sold in Hokkaido aren't actually made with chicken.
北海道卖的烤鸡便当 不是真的用烤鸡
They use pork instead.
而是用猪肉哦
What is wrong with this world?
这世界到底怎么了?
You two better hurry up or we'll finish the meat.
你们两个 烤肉快被吃完咯
TO: AYA-CHAN THE FLOWERS ARE IN FULL BLOOM.
(小绫 全开了 好漂亮)
Akari's sound asleep.
朱莉已经睡着了呢
Well, she was running all over the place.
毕竟她一直跑来跑去 到处玩啊
Still,
话说回来
it's pitch black here at night since there are no streetlights.
这里完全没有路灯 到了晚上就会变得黑漆漆的呢
In that case,
那么
how about using this?
这样如何?
I have one too!
我也有哦
I brought mine as well.
我也有带
Geez,
什么嘛
you guys should've brought them out sooner!
既然有带的话 就早点拿出来呀
Putting all these lights together really creates a different ambience.
把这么多灯放在一起 变得很有气氛呢
What's up?
怎么了?
Everyone, come here with your lanterns!
大家拿着提灯过来这里
What a sight!
真壮观呢
Oh, that looks comfy.
那样看起来好舒服
It's so beautiful…
好漂亮哦
I never thought you could enjoy cherry blossoms this way.
没想到还能这样子赏樱呢
Get ready.
要拍咯
My album's filled to the brim with cherry blossoms.
相簿里全是樱花了
Same.
我懂
Hey, hey…
欸…
Let's each show the best cherry blossom picture we have.
我们来互相展示自己手机里 最棒的樱花照片吧
Good idea!
好主意
Which one should I choose?
要选哪张呢
Ready when you guys are.
说完预备 就要拿出来哦
Ready!
预备
Ena chose a picture with Chikuwa.
惠那选了和竹轮去赏樱的照片啊
That's right.
没错
Chikuwa's so cute!
竹轮好可爱哦
Where was this, Rin?
凛 这是哪里呀?
Mt. Fuji in the background
背景的富士山
makes these cherry blossoms look even more spectacular.
显得这些樱花特别壮观呢
This was a place called Tokakyo Park, I think.
好像是叫桃花桥公园吧
I discovered it by chance while biking to see cherry blossoms.
是我骑车去赏樱时 偶然发现的
That's the essence of cherry blossom viewing by bike.
这就是骑车赏樱的醍醐味呢
Aki's cherry blossoms look unique too.
明的樱花也很有趣呢
They actually bloom on the trunk!
居然开在树干上
Yeah.
对啊
I think they call them "doufuki sakura".
好像叫做"胴吹樱"
I like them because they look strong and lively.
看起来很强大 所以我特别喜欢
Aoi, your whole screen is pink!
小葵 你整个屏幕都是粉红色的耶
Those are cherry blossoms near my house.
这是我家附近的樱花
They've grown so big that I can't fit them all into one photo.
已经大到没办法完全拍进去了
The only issue is
唯一有问题的
Nadeshiko's photo.
就是抚子了
Those cherry blossoms haven't even bloomed yet!
那张照片的樱花根本还没开花嘛
That's what you all think, hm?
大家肯定都是这么想的吧?
I'll show you a magic trick!
给你们变个魔术吧
They bloomed!
开花了
For real?
真的假的啊
Amazing!
好厉害
Are those cherry blossoms on the way to school?
这是上学路上的樱花吗
They sure are.
没错
I take photos of them every time I pass by.
我每次经过都会帮它拍照
When did you start taking them?
你从什么时候开始拍的啊
Around early March.
大概是3月初吧
but then they all bloomed at once.
一开始完全没有变化 后来却一口气全都开了
And it didn't end there.
而且不是这样就结束咯
I continued taking photos
后来
until the cherry blossoms fell
我还持续拍到樱花凋谢
and new green leaves sprouted.
直到绿芽长出来为止
Nadeshiko always does things out of the box.
抚子做的事情真有趣呢
I never expected such a big change in just a few weeks.
没想到短短几个礼拜 居然可以有这么大的变化
That's right! We need to make some changes too!
没错 我们也得改变才行
What are you going on about?
突然说什么啊
After this spring break,
这个春假过后
we'll be in second year.
我们就升上二年级了
It'll also be the second year since our club was established.
也是野活会成立的第二年
That's why…
所以无论如何
"OUTDOOR ACTIVITIES CLUB" We have to become an official club
(野外活动社) 我们都要变成社团
We'll finally upgrade
这样就能从同好会活动
to a full-fledged club.
晋级成社团活动了呢
Club activities!
社团活动
But what are the benefits of becoming an official club?
不过变成社团后 有什么好处吗
Well…
这个嘛
I can't drink anymore.
我已经喝不下了
Generally,
整体来说
we can apply for club funding,
就是可以申请社团经费
and with more club members,
社团成员也会越来越多
we may be able to get a bigger clubroom.
或许就能换到一个 更大的社团办公室了
Our current one is small and cosy,
其实现在的小房间也挺温馨的啦
but with more members,
社团成员增加后
we'll get to do even more activities.
能做的事情也会越变越多吧
Exactly!
正是如此
So we must do our best to get more members!
所以我们要努力招揽新成员
Everyone, put out your lanterns!
大家把提灯都关掉
Why?
为什么?
Don't ask questions.
别问为什么了
Ready? Let's do it!
要关咯 预备…
Not only did we get to see the night cherry blossoms,
不仅能看到樱花 还能欣赏满月
Beautiful.
真漂亮呢
You're up early, Rin-chan.
小凛 你起得好早哦
Morning.
早安
Want some cocoa?
要喝可可吗
Sure.
好啊…
Here you go.
来
Thanks.
谢谢
I enjoyed solo-camping and camping with you and Aya-chan,
虽然我也很喜欢单人露营 以及跟小绫三个人去露营的感觉
but it's fun to go camping with everyone together too.
但像这样大家一起露营也很有趣呢
Yeah.
是啊
Thanks for inviting me.
谢谢你约我来露营
Next time, it's my turn.
下次换我约你
Timing is everything, isn't it?
时机这种东西 还真难抓呢
Nade…
抚…
Rin-chan.
小凛
Where should we go next time?
下次要去哪里呢
I heard from Sakura
我听姐姐说
that there's a railway heritage park in Gunma.
群马有个铁道博物馆
What do you think of a retro train camp?
你觉得复古电车考察露营怎么样?
So, they have a railway heritage park.
原来那边有铁道博物馆啊
Seems like camping in Gunma would be interesting.
看来去群马露营应该也很有趣呢
Right?
对吧
I want to go to Saitama too.
我还想去埼玉看看
I live so close to it, but I've never been there.
虽然就在隔壁 但我从没有去过
I heard there's a shrine dedicated to wolves there.
听说那边还有个祭拜狼的神社呢
When the weather warms up a bit,
等天气再暖和一点
I also want to visit northern Nagano.
我也想去长野北部看看
And have soba noodles in Togakushi.
还要在户隐吃荞麦面
Or go a bit further north to Niigata.
或者再往北走一点 去新潟那里
Preparing camp meals with seafood from the Sea of Japan sounds nice too.
用日本海的海鲜 做露营料理感觉也不错
Niigata, huh?
新潟啊
There are several well-known camping gear manufacturers there.
那边有几间知名的露营用品制造商
Might be fun checking them out.
去四处参观一下应该很有趣
For camping enthusiasts,
对露营爱好者来说
Niigata is the sacred land.
新潟可是个圣地呢
They've got Lake Inawashiro
隔壁的福岛县
in Fukushima too.
也有一个叫猪苗代湖的湖泊
It's famous in the camping world.
在露营界很有名哦
Grandpa told me about Mt. Bandai next to that lake.
我曾经听爷爷说过 那座湖泊旁边的磐梯山
It's a beautiful hiking spot.
是个漂亮的跑山景点
Let's invite Aya-chan to go together
那就约小绫一起去
and have another motorbike camping trip!
再来场机车露营吧
Shizuoka to Fukushima is a bit far though, isn't it?
从静冈到福岛有点太远了吧
All right.
很好
Oh no! I'm going to be late!
糟糕 得加紧脚步了
Cycling to school is pretty nice.
骑自行车上学 感觉挺不错的呢
Culinary club!
我们是料理研究社
Let's get creative with cooking!
一起来做创意料理吧
-We're the calligraphy club. -Put your blood, tears, and sweat in Judo!
-我们是书法社 -来我们柔道社 跟我们一起流汗吧
This is the swim club!
我们是游泳社
We're aiming for nationals!
目标是参加全国大赛
Everyone's so competitive.
大家都好拼哦
Have you decided which club you want to join?
你决定好要参加哪个社团了吗
Not yet.
还没
They don't seem to have an illustration club here.
看来这里没有插画研究社
I see…
这样啊
Judo!
我们是柔道社
Calligraphy!
我们是书法社
Culinary!
我们是料理研究社
OUTDOOR ACTIVITIES CLUB
(野外活动同好会)
Come and camp with us!
来露营吧
We're the Outdoor Activities Club!
我们是野外活动同好会
Our target: to become an official club!
目标是成为社团
OUTDOOR ACTIVITIES CLUB
(野外活动同好会)
All done!
完成
All that's left is to colour this and use it
接下来只要上色
to recruit the new first years.
再拿去招聘一年级参加就好
I'll go borrow some art supplies from the art club.
我去跟美术社借画图用具
You can do that after school…
那个放学后再借也可以
Rin-chan!
小凛
Good morning!
早安
Good morning, Nadeshiko.
抚子 早安
You're in a good mood this morning, Nadeshiko.
你一大早就看起来很开心呢 抚子
Oh, don't mind me. It's nothing.
抱歉…没什么